i'm going to share several critical
things about prolonged fasting
that you need to know
fasting is very simple okay it shouldn't
be that hard some people overthink it
and those things that are really simple
are usually extremely powerful
and that's what fasting is i mean it's
actually mind-blowing to think that the
absence of food just not eating can
create so many powerful effects and if
you haven't tried it you should
definitely try it in order to understand
the benefits of fasting you want to
compare it to
another subject and usually a subject
that would be the opposite okay and that
would be
snacking okay if you look at what
snacking does to the human body
it is absolutely positively devastating
in fact i think out of all the things
that you can do
that create a negative influence on your
body snacking is at the top of the list
because of what it does to insulin it's
a chronic
increase in elevation of insulin which
then leads to just a million other
problems i mean when you think about it
i guess i'll just pull this up right
here real
quick
i don't think you can ever heal the body
with eating frequent meals okay we have
this idea that you have to heal the body
with food right like food is nourishing
actually it might be nourishing but to
really heal you're better off
not eating
um this idea that breakfast is the most
important meal is a total lie and i used
to promote it before i learned otherwise
what about promoting like bedtime snacks
for kids right or after school snacks or
this advice that you should never miss a
meal right
which i have no idea who started that
well actually i do
it's the snack food industry that
started that and for some reason this
snacking food industry just doesn't like
me for some reason i don't know why it
is so if we look at snacking snacking
actually
makes you more hungry because you're
eating a small amount of calories and
you're stimulating insulin and that
lowers your blood sugar about an hour
and a half later so you're going to
stimulate hunger
not stimulate your metabolism okay
you're going to stimulate hunger
when you snack
and it's going to promote
more
hunger okay so and you're never ever
going to fix hypoglycemia
by
eating these snacks
because it just it keeps that
hypoglycemic low blood sugar thing going
on and on and on in fact it actually
slows your metabolism or shall i say
slows your ability to lose weight
because you develop insulin resistance
because you have this constant increase
of insulin and also it's going to
promote a need for a nap okay right
after you eat you're going to feel like
you need a nap and you may find that
eating does reduce moodiness and
grouchiness but soon after about an hour
later when your blood sugars are dropped
you're going to revert back to this
moodiness
now in history
a lot of great thinkers
have commented on fasting and had
something to say about fasting
hippocrates
said to eat when you are sick is to fuel
your
illness
fascinating right
and then we have the ancient greek
philosophers right the great thinkers
pythagoras pythagoras required fasting
of his students okay so they can think
more clearly plato aristotle were
advocates of fasting ben franklin said
the best of all medicine
is rest
and fasting
mark twain said a little starvation can
really do more for the average sick
person
than the best medicine and the best
doctors and another very interesting
point about your fat okay your adipose
tissue
where did it come from why did we
develop this fat tissue that you hate so
much well we developed it from
scarcity of food okay food scarcity and
what this fat really is it's a it's an
efficient way of surviving it's a way to
make your energy very efficient and when
some people express that they have a
damaged or slow or ruined metabolism
what they really have is an efficient
metabolism because now the body can go
with just a little bit of food for long
periods of time and that fat is retained
so fat is all about prolonging fuel
it's all about helping you survive when
there's no food so therein lies the
secret to losing fat okay
can you do it by adding more food by
eating something no you want to mimic
why we developed it in the first place
we want to mimic
starvation but not really starvation i
want to actually kind of
clarify what i mean by a mimic okay the
difference between fasting and
starvation really has to do with one
thing control who's in control when
you're fasting you're in control when
you're starving you're usually
being controlled by the environment
because there's no food
so if we were going to mimic starvation
we're really being in control because we
could eat if we want right and so the
secret to getting rid of your fat really
is just to
do prolonged
fasting okay the power of prolonged
fasting is just remarkable for your
health so let's go through the seven
critical things that you need to know
okay
the first thing i want to mention is
that
when you do
fasting
you really only want to drink water you
can have tea
you can have some coffee
but you definitely want to take
supplements and the reason is because
nowadays people are so deficient in
nutrients so even though when you go
through fasting your body
adapts and becomes very efficient at
holding nutrients and the requirement of
nutrients is a lot less you could still
have certain deficiencies of both trace
minerals especially and other things
like electrolytes and
even the b vitamins so i recommend
taking your supplements and the two main
categories of supplements i would
recommend are the electrolytes
and the b vitamins but of course if you
can also do some other ones like
vitamin d
vitamin c that would be
important what you don't want to do is
you don't want to do like branch chain
amino acids you don't want to have
little
snacks
no you don't want to do that and there
are some programs that promote that but
i don't recommend that because what
you're going to do is you're going to
inhibit this very powerful thing that
gives you
huge benefits okay called autophagy what
is that
that is a condition it's not a thing
it's a condition in your body
that
basically recycles old damaged proteins
okay so
fasting is the most potent
trigger to
autophagy and so autophagy is kind of
like self-cleaning it's cleaning up the
old dead proteins it's cleaning up
pathogens in the body it's stimulating
all sorts of genes for long-term
survival and longevity
it helps to clean up
damaged mitochondria which is directly
behind the root cause of cancer so this
is why
prolonged fasting is the best solution
to cancer
and if you have not seen my videos
on two amazing
success stories with cancer
like stage four cancer i'm gonna put
those down below
but it's very powerful so autophagy is a
condition
where you're recycling like damaged
protein i'm talking about amyloid
plaquing that's involved in alzheimer's
talking about the um the damaged protein
involved in chronic disease like in your
eyes like from diabetes
from chronic inflammation
and by the way when you start doing
prolonged fasting you can just
erase any inflammation in the body and
it's
amazing for autoimmune type conditions
as well so we're recycling damaged
proteins not just your muscles but
proteins involved in the enzymes the all
the different metabolic pathways the
things that are damaged it cleans all
that up
so just make sure you do uh your water
you know a couple other things like tea
and coffee in your supplements but
nothing else okay
the other thing i want to bring up is
the amount of water i would recommend at
least two and a half
liters of water now there are dry fast
and that's a whole different thing but
for most of you watching i i don't
recommend you do that do a water fast so
you're basically drinking a good amount
of water
what's interesting about doing a fast
your body will make its own water out of
fat but that's for another video
i just recommend you drink enough water
and the reason i recommend you drink
water is when you start fasting
boy you just dump your glycogen okay
your stored sugar
and you're burning up the sugar first
and then
with that um
is the release of a lot of fluids
because
you have a tremendous amount of water
that's tied in with this stored
blood sugar in your muscles and your in
your liver so you're going to get rid of
a good amount of fluid initially and
with that
becomes a loss of electrolytes so you
want to put back in those electrolytes
probably the biggest risk of doing these
fast okay
is when you're doing them without
electrolytes because uh you can create a
lot of
problems with your heart
you can you can faint
you can even have heart attacks why
because you're you're basically
depriving your body of key
uh electrolytes and realize that sodium
chloride is also
part of electrolytes okay so you need
salt and other electrolytes
if you feel weakness in your muscles
that is an indication that you need
more
salt okay and of course i'm talking
about sea salt and electrolytes
i'm also talking about potassium
magnesium
calcium
things like that now
let's go into number three refeeding
this is when you
start to eat again now i'm not talking
about
intermittent fasting right now i'm
talking about prolonged fasting when
you're fasting 48 72 hours you're
fasting five days you're fasting you
know 14 days 21 days
30 days whatever
and you could do a five day or even a 21
day fast several times to the year
and
just keep your health at a whole new
level
the some of the problems with fasting
that i want to bring up is like you
don't want to do fasting when you're
pregnant when you're lactating
you don't want to do fasting if you have
anorexia however
if you have stage four cancer
or
cancer in general
personally i would do prolonged fasting
immediately so if you're doing a
prolonged fast all right
what do you eat
coming off the fast
well you want to do
something healthy of course
but you don't want to do a big meal okay
and you especially do not want to do
something with refined carbs and sugar
and the reason is because you're going
to create a huge shift of potassium okay
out of the cell and 98 of all your
potassium should be inside that cell
and so
in order to store sugar you need
potassium so you're going to just suck
out this potassium
too fast
and you're going to end up with a severe
imbalance uh of potassium in the blood
inside the cell there's going to be this
huge imbalance and that can create some
dangers so do not
do
you know just regular foods or refined
carbs when you come off
this prolonged fast instead do a little
bit of salad maybe a little egg
just a little bit of something and then
wait for a couple hours and then you can
maybe have a little bit of nuts
and wait for a little bit do a little
avocado and gradually kind of come out
of this okay you do not want to do a big
meal
like i did and that was a really good
demonstration of what not to do because
i just pigged out i ate all this food at
this huge meal
and oh my goodness did i
end up with a serious
uh digestive problem
tired and i'm like okay i will never do
that again in fact i need to have other
people learn from my mistakes
all right if you're doing a prolonged
fast and i'm saying
probably 72 hours or longer realize that
all these ketones are going to make you
pretty acid it's not a bad thing it's
just that if you're doing apple cider
vinegar and you're adding that you're
going to add some more acidity and that
can throw off your ph and you may find
that your your pulse rate it's like a
very loud pounding
pulse rate in your ear that's going to
make it difficult to sleep because your
ph is off and your breathing might be
affected too like like air hunger like
can't get enough air so don't just don't
do the apple cider vinegar if you're
doing a fast longer than 72 hours you
may want to do some baking soda just a
little bit like a an eighth of a
teaspoon in some water and drink that
especially if you start having a
build-up of like a gout symptom from the
uric acid that goes up uric acid is one
of the most powerful antioxidants in
your blood and it's a normal thing but
some people that are predisposed to gout
might have a flare-up especially when
they
are doing this initially okay but
normally it's not a situation and number
five do the healthy version of the
ketogenic diet don't just go back to
regular foods because first of all the
carbs are going to kind of nullify some
of the benefits that you had okay
because this this whole goal of doing
fasting is to get rid of the bad effects
of a high carb diet and a junk food diet
so why would you want to go back to that
so i would highly recommend combining
healthy keto with the intermittent
fasting
okay number six dawn phenomenon
what is that that has to do with your
blood sugars going up
okay maybe between five
in the morning to eight like all of a
sudden your blood sugars go up like you
didn't eat any sugar where is that sugar
coming from well your liver is making
sugar okay there's a problem with
insulin resistance
which is still occurring because it
takes
a quite a while to get rid of that
condition it could take months
even up to a year or a little bit longer
to fully get rid of that if you have the
dawn phenomenon all that means is that
you have insulin resistance okay
and i wouldn't worry about it too much
however if it concerns you i would go
for a long walk and just burn off that
sugar
it's not coming from your diet okay it's
just your liver is making the sugar
and that's a big difference between
consuming sugar all right it's
you're not going to have a problem and
also that problem is going to go away
with time
versus some people might think oh
fasting is bad because it raised my
sugar so i'm going to stop doing that
that would be a mistake and so a couple
other little things you can do you can
probably take berberine or other things
like cinnamon to help
reduce insulin resistance okay all right
number seven knowing when to break your
fast
now should you just dive right into a
prolonged fast
well you know what you could you could
are you going to feel great maybe not
especially if you haven't fasted you're
gonna have to go through a period of
time where your body adapts and so it
might take you several days before you
start feeling good
so a lot of people do this gradually and
they kind of ease into it after doing
you know weeks of intermittent fasting
so
you could just cold turkey just jump
right in and do prolonged fasting okay
however when you start fasting
what you're really doing is you're
switching from the glucose fuel
to the fat fuel okay and then also the
body then has to make new enzymes for
ketones okay so your body actually is
running on fatty acids
as well as ketones especially for your
brain your brain can't run in fatty
acids it runs on ketones so
just think about this you're not going
to feel really good in your head when
you start doing fasting simply because
it takes a while to develop ketones so
in the meantime what you could do is
take mct oil or you can take ketone
supplements
and get rid of those symptoms however
you may not feel good mentally
at first but then you start adapting and
your appetite goes away and you feel
good
that's a really good indication that
you've adapted okay so if you're doing
this gradual okay
there's always going to be a transition
phase where you're going to have to go
through something
that's going to be uncomfortable but
just realize push through that like you
might have hunger
pains you might feel
a little bit kind of off
but then
if you push through that
that will go away
because your body
has is forced to adapt to this new
method of burning fuel there's no other
shortcuts other than just pushing
through that sometimes so at some point
going from intermittent fasting to
prolonged fasting you're going to have
to go through
a little bit of this transition it's
normal it's not abnormal
i'm just letting you know
before you go through it so you can
not be freaked out about it but when i
say don't eat if you're not hungry eat
when you're hungry
i'm mainly talking about doing
intermittent fasting
but when we get into prolonged fasting
should you eat when you're hungry
no actually we're going to just push
through that
to the other side
okay so that's kind of a little bit of a
little point i want to bring up
now since we're on the topic of fasting
i think it'd be very important for you
to learn a little bit more about
how to speed up the process and that
would be how to make insulin more
sensitive so you should watch this video
right here